Guide to the Richard Pratt Collection, 1820-2005 AIS.1998.03
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Richard Pratt Collection
1920-2005
1920-1998
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Pratt, Richard H.
AIS.1998.03
40.95 Linear Feet (78 boxes)
This collection contains the professional, personal, and family materials of Richard H. Pratt, Professor Emeritus, Department of Physics, University of Pittsburgh. Richard Pratt is a major contributor to the field of atomic physics as well as an active environmentalist and experienced world traveler. This collection is comprised mainly of both professional and personal correspondence, 1925-2005, but also includes articles, notes, manuscripts, meeting minutes, and publications from his professional life; and photographs of his family. Richard Pratt's materials include the years - 1940-2005. The Pratt family materials include the years - 1820-1997.
Biography
Richard Pratt, Professor Emeritus at the University of Pittsburgh, is a well known contributor and leader in the field of high energy atomic physics, as well as being an active environmentalist and experienced world traveler. He is also known for his assistance in the defection of many physicists from communist eastern bloc countries including Romania in the 1970s. Pratt was also involved in bringing Semester at Sea, a teaching voyage that circumnavigates the globe during a semester, to the University of Pittsburgh as well as being one of the first chairs of the local Sierra Club chapter.
Richard Houghton Pratt was born on May 5, 1934 in New York City. At the age of four he moved to Mount Pleasant, Michigan, attended elementary school where he was two years younger than his classmates, having started kindergarten early and taking grades 3-4 in one year and attended Mount Pleasant High School, 1946-50, where he was Valedictorian. In the fall of 1950, Richard Pratt went to the University of Chicago on a tuition scholarship, having placed out of most college courses Pratt graduated in just two years at age eighteen. Following graduation Pratt was a National Science Foundation Fellow for one year before receiving his masters of science in 1955, and Ph.D. in 1959, both from the University of Chicago. While at the University of Chicago he took the last quantum mechanics course taught by Enrico Fermi
During Pratt's education at the University of Chicago he met his wife, Ann. Elizabeth Ann Glass, was born January 2, 1933 in Orange, New Jersey. She was a math-pre-med major at Oberlin College and came to the University of Chicago for graduate school in microbiology in 1954. The Pratts were married in Chicago on November 1, 1958. A year later, after finishing his Ph.D., Richard accepted a post-doc position at Stanford University. Richard worked at Stanford as a research associate (1959-1961) and as an assistant professor (1961-1964) and Ann completed her Ph.D.. While teaching at Stanford he began a long relationship as a consultant for the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory at the University of California. In 1964 the Pratts moved to Pittsburgh where Richard accepted a job as associate professor in the Department of Physics and Astronomy at the University of Pittsburgh and Ann worked as an assistant professor at the University of Pittsburgh. She later had a research position at Carnegie Mellon University where she became a research scientist. Richard became a full professor in 1969 and a professor emeritus after his retirement in 1999. Richard and Ann have four children: Jonathan, Kathryn, Caroline and Paul.
While working in atomic physics at the University of Pittsburgh, Richard Pratt ran the high energy theory group which was supported at various times by the Department of Energy and the National Science Foundation. He worked primarily in relativistic electron-photon radiation interaction processes in the atomic field creating main world codes. Pratt was in charge of graduate admissions for the department as well as the graduate research committee. The Physics Department eventually expanded into high energy experiment, astrophysics, and condensed matter. Richard Pratt also helped organize the International Radiation Physics Society (IRPS), in 1985, serving as secretary and president. Pratt's other university activities included the University Senate where he was a member and chair of the Senate Budget Policies Committee, and chair of the Educational Policies Committee which brought Semester at Sea to the University of Pittsburgh. Semester at Sea is a study abroad opportunity for undergraduate students to travel the globe on a cruise ship while taking university courses for credit. Pratt has been involved with Semester at Sea from the beginning of its University of Pittsburgh Program including being Academic Dean in fall 1984 and Administrative Dean in 1990, as well as teaching and being a member of the advisory board.
Richard has been involved in many environmental organizations, one of which is the Sierra Club. Richard and Ann Pratt joined the Sierra Club in 1965, shortly after moving to Pittsburgh. In 1970 Richard was invited to a meeting to organize a group in Pittsburgh. He served as the first vice-chair of the Allegheny Group eventually becoming its chair, 1974-1976. He worked on the designation of wilderness areas in the Allegheny National Forest including Tracy Ridge and the Allegheny Front, both of which became National Recreation Areas. In 1973 a hiking program was established and Richard has led hikes, at least once a month, ever since. Richard was chair of the Pennsylvania Chapter, 1976-1980, which included being chair at the time of the Three Mile Island nuclear accident in Harrisburg, PA. He served on the Governor's Science Council for Pennsylvania including its Energy Facility Sitting Task Force. Richard also served on, and was chair of, the Appalachian Regional Conservation Committee; Sierra Club Regional Vice President, 1982-1983; and was a member of the Sierra Club National Council, 1980-1982.
This collection also includes a collection of materials from Richard Pratt's extended family including his parents, Karl and Gertrude Pratt; his grandparents, Burton and Mary Luella Pratt, of Wellington, OH; and members of his Mother's side of the family, the Gennis Family, of New York City.
Scope and Content Notes
The Collection of Richard Pratt, 1820-2005, contains four separate series. Series I. Richard Pratt Professional, 1950-2004, spans Richard Pratt's professional career, from an undergraduate at the University of Chicago to Professor Emeritus at the University of Pittsburgh. This series includes three subseries: Subseries 1. contains materials related to Richard Pratt's education and professional positions including class notes, bibliographies, awards, workbooks, group meeting notices, and funding proposals. Subseries 2. includes memos, journals, and correspondence regarding Pratt's involvement with Semester at Sea. Subseries 3. contains professional correspondence. These materials are arranged chronologically by subject and more information can be found in the series and subseries scope notes.
Series II. contains materials related to Richard Pratt's non-professional life, 1940-2005. This series includes three subseries: 1. General Materials, 1940-1978 includes hiking journals, elementary and high school manuscripts, correspondence regarding trips to Quebec and Cuba, passports, and address books; 2. Family Correspondence, 1940-2005 includes letters between Richard and his parents, letters written to his extended family, Christmas letters written to friends and colleagues, and letters between Richard and his wife, Ann and their children; and 3. Personal Correspondence, 1943-1999 including letters between the Pratts and friends, colleagues, and extended family. Additional information concerning these materials can be found at the series and subseries scope content notes.
Series III. consists of materials relating to Richard Pratt involvement with the Sierra Club, 1973-1998. This series contains publications, history, bylaws, minutes, proposals, and trip reports and is arranged chronologically by subject. Richard Pratt's history of involvement can be found in his biography. Series IV. contains materials related to the Pratt family, 1820-1997. This series contains four subseries: subseries 1. contains materials that represent the professional career of Richard Pratt's father - Karl Pratt, Professor of Psychology at Central Michigan University, 1920-1989. This subseries contains resumes, articles, manuscripts, reprints, article/book reviews, and correspondence. This subseries is also arranged chronologically by subject.
Subseries 2. consists of the personal materials of Karl and Gertrude Pratt (Richard's Parents), 1911-1997. This subseries is organized into three sections: General Materials, 1911-1989; Family Correspondence, 1919-1997; and Personal Correspondence, 1919-1997. The first section contains diaries, journals, account books, correspondence, and essays, the bulk of which represent Karl's adolescence, travels, and attempts at writing fiction, 1911-1930. The second section contains family correspondence, 1919-1997. This subseries includes correspondence between Karl and Gertrude Pratt, mostly between 1933-1937, after Richard was born and living in New York with his Mother while his Father worked in Michigan; other correspondence includes Karl Pratt to/from his mother Mary Luella and sister Mildred Pratt (Needles); Karl and Gertrude to/from the Gennis family (Gertrude's family); and Karl and Gertrude to/from Richard Pratt's children. The third section consists of other personal correspondence to/from Karl and Gertrude Pratt and is arranged chronologically and alphabetically.
Subseries 3. contains materials, mostly correspondence, from other members of Pratt's extended family. Family members include Burton and Mary Luella Pratt, Richard's Grandparents; Benjamin and Alta Pratt, Burton's Brother and various other family members. Some of this material dates back to the 1840s and 1850s and includes correspondence, notebooks, account books, invitations, manuscripts, and other materials, 1820-1960. Subseries 4. contains photographs of Richard, Ann, Karl, Gertrude, and various Pratt and Gennis family members, 1860s-1940s. Inventories are available if noted at the folder level.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Accruals
Additional material received in 2004 and 2005.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Richard Pratt in 1998.
Previous Citation
Richard Pratt Collection, 1820-2005, AIS.1998.03, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Mount Pleasant (Mich.); Huntington (Ohio); Wellington (Ohio); Hiking -- Pennsylvania; Green movement -- Pennsylvania; Environmentalism -- Pennsylvania; Psychology -- Study and teaching; Physics -- Studying and teaching; Physics teachers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Environment; Personal papers; University of Pittsburgh; Institute for Shipboard Education (University of Pittsburgh); Pratt family; International Radiation Physics Society; Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory; Pratt, Richard H.; Sierra Club. Pennsylvania Chapter. Allegheny Group; Stanford University. Department of Physics; University of Chicago. Department of Physics; University of Pittsburgh. Department of Physics and Astronomy; Fermi, Enrico; Gennis family
- Richard Pratt Professional, 1950-2004; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I contains materials related to Richard Pratt's undergraduate and graduate education, positions held at the University of Chicago, Stanford University, and the University of Pittsburgh, various consultant positions, and professional memberships. This series also includes proposals for projects and collaborations with physicists of other nations including China, India, Russia, and Romania, among others. The bulk of this series is correspondence, but also includes workbooks (tracking meetings and trips), meeting notices of Pratt's atomic physics group, proposals, lab reports, course information, memos, and agreements.
  This series is organized into subseries. These include: Subseries 1. Education and Positions, 1950-2004, which consists of undergraduate and graduate school at the University of Chicago, job searches, vitas, bibliography, and awards. Subseries I. also includes workbooks and group meeting notices, 1979-2004, that include workbooks that track Pratt's activities including meetings, travels, and notes; group meeting notices; and materials concerning consulting positions (National Science Foundation, Livermore National Laboratory), international research proposals, and research trips. This subseries also includes correspondence regarding Pratt's help in the defection of Romanian Physicists to the United States in the 1970s. Subseries 2. Semester at Sea, 1984-1992, contains materials regarding the Semester at Sea Program at the University of Pittsburgh. Subseries 3. contains professional correspondence, 1959-1999.
  - Education and Positions, 1950-2004; 1.
    Subseries 1. consists of admissions, articles, and notes from undergraduate and graduate school at the University of Chicago, ditto copies of notes from the last Quantum Physics course taught by Enrico Fermi, job searches, vitas, bibliography, and awards. This subseries also contains workbooks used by Pratt to keep track of his activities including meetings, travels, and notes. Also included are Pratt's group meeting notices and minutes. The group meetings are held weekly on a semi-regular basis (depending on who is traveling), and are attended by Pratt's graduate students and colleagues, both from Pittsburgh and international visiting scholars. Organizational issues, literature reviews, and abstract deadlines are discussed as well as upcoming travel and visitor schedules. These materials are summaries of the meetings, 1979-2004, and include information on projects and theories being researched.
    This subseries also includes materials related to National Science Foundation and Lawrence Livermore Laboratory funding sources. The Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory at the University of California is one of the main government weapons laboratories. Richard Pratt became a consultant there in 1959 while he was at Stanford. Scientists at the lab were interested in Pratt's thesis work as it suggested an error, in the work of Hall, employed by the lab, and Oppenheimer, on the high energy limit of photoeffect and helped to assemble a group for further numerical calculations at lower energies. A couple of years after moving to Pittsburgh he became a consultant again and arranged for subcontracts for the University of Pittsburgh for further work in photoeffect, bremsstrahlung, and photon atom scattering. This led to further work for graduate students. Pratt was also successful in receiving funding from a series of National Science Foundation grants for cooperative research with Universities and Institutions in various parts of the world. Pratt also served as a Program Director for the National Science Foundation, 1987-1989. Much of Pratt's current work has proceeded through these continuing contacts.
    - University of Chicago Admissions, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - University of Chicago Correspondence, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Enrico Fermi's Quantum Physics Course, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
    - Journal, Physical Review, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Job Searches, tanford University, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Job Searches, Other, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Job Searches, University of Pittsburgh, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Job Searches, Other, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Job Applications, 1976-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Vitas, 1965-1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bibliography, 1957-2002 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Meetings/Talks, 1958-1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Salary Letters, 1960-1998 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Awards, 1988-1998 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Pittsburgh Informal Program, 1980-2004 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Workbooks, April 1981 - January 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Workbooks, January 1983 - November 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2-15)
    - Workbooks, December 1995 - November 2000 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - Group Meeting Notices, 1979-1984 (Box 3, Folder 4-9)
    - Group Meeting Notices, 1985-1989 (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
    - Group Meeting Notices, 1990-1993 (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
    - Group Meeting Notices, 1994-2000 (Box 6, Folder 1-7)
    - Group Meeting Notices, 2001-2004 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
    - Group Meeting Notices, Group Secretary, 1967-1988 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - National Science Foundation, Position, 1987-1989, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, University of Pittsburgh, 1977-1982 (Box 7, Folder 8-11)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, University of Pittsburgh, 1979-1996 (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, Argentina, 1992-1995 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, Brazil, 1992-1995 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, China, 1987-1991 (Box 8, Folder 9-11)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, Croatia, 1987-1990, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, India, 1978-1994 (Box 9, Folder 3-7)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, Israel, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, Korea, 1988-1995 (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, Latvia, 1997 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, Malaysia, 1984-1997 (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, Poland-Rochester-Pittsburgh, 1980-1983, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, Romania, 1991-1994 (Box 10, Folder 3-6)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, Russia, 1992-1998 (Box 10, Folder 7-14)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, Taiwan, 1979-1981 (Box 10, Folder 15-16)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, Other Awards, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 17)
    - National Science Foundation, Proposals and Awards, NETL Bremsstrahlung, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, Romanian Physicists- Bunaciu, Doina, 1980-1981 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, Romanian Physicists- Foias, Ciprian, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, Romanian Physicists- Gavrila, Mihai, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Romanian Physicists- Patrulius, Radu, 1969-1980 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Romanian Physicists- Pomponiu, Constantin, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - "Memo of Understanding", University of Pittsburgh - University of Bucharest, 1972-1977 (Box 11, Folder 4-7)
    - Institutions in Romania, 1970-1972 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Institutions in Poland, 1971-1982 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Ukraine Trip, 1997-1998 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Evaluation at Bose Institute, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - CISA, Israel-Pittsburgh Cooperation, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Asilomar Workshop, 1984-1985 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Darjeeling Workshop, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Security Clearance, 1958-2000 (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
    - Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Lab Reports, November 1969 - December 1974 (Box 12, Folder 4-7)
    - Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Subcontract, 1971-1996 (Box 13, Folder 1-8)
    - Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Consulting, 1987-1988 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Semester at Sea, 1984-1992; 2.
    Subseries 2. contains materials regarding Richard Pratt's involvement in bringing the Semester at Sea Program to the University of Pittsburgh; serving as Academic Dean in 1984; and as Administrative Dean in 1990. Records include correspondence about sponsorship, appointments, reports, memos, programs, mailings, and notebooks. This subseries is arranged chronologically.
    - Pittsburgh Sponsorship and Evaluation, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Appointments and Reports, 1985 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Courses, 1986 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Dean's Memo, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Directory, 1988 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Evening Programs, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Field Programs, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - General, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - General Mailings, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Voyage Notebooks, 1984-1990 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Journal, 1990 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1999; 3.
    Subseries 3. consists of professional correspondence to/from Richard Pratt. The correspondence concerns his work with colleagues and students in many fields of physics. The correspondence files have been retained in original order and are organized in two ways - correspondence grouped by first letter of last name; and correspondence organized alphabetically by last name. If a researcher wishes to look up an individual it is recommended to look in both sections.
    - A-B (Box 14, Folder 10-11)
    - C-R (Box 15, Folder 1-16)
    - R-Z (Box 16, Folder 1-4)
    - Amusia, Miron Ya. (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Basavaraju, G. (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Bechler, Adam (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Beigman, Israel L. (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Birula, Iwo Bialynicki (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Bunaciu, Doina (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Chernysheva, Larissa V. (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Cionga, Aurelia (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - Costescu, Adrian (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - Dondera, Mihai (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - Dutt, Ranabir (Dr.) (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - Feng, I-Jaung (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - Fink, Joanne K. (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - Florescu, Viorica (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - Erzeneoglu, Salih Z. (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - Gabriel, Oscar (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - Gailite (Karule), Erna (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Gavrila, Mihai (Box 16, Folder 22)
    - Ghose, A.M. (Box 16, Folder 23)
    - Goldberg, Isser Benjamin (Box 16, Folder 24)
    - Gonclaves, Odiar D. (Box 16, Folder 25)
    - Govinda, Nayak (Box 16, Folder 26)
    - Huang, Keh-Ning (Box 16, Folder 27)
    - Ivinski, Zbigniew (Box 16, Folder 28)
    - Kane, Prabhakar P. (Box 16, Folder 29)
    - Kissel, Lynn (Box 16, Folder 30)
    - Kim, Longhaun (Box 16, Folder 31)
    - Kim, Young Soon (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Lamourex, M. (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Lee, Chia-Ming (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Liang, Xiaoling (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Liu, Lei (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Lyalin, Andrey G. (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Magargee, Mary (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Manakov, Nikolai L. (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Marian, Tudor (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - McEnnan, James (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - Miraglia, Jorgr E. (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Namyslowski, J.M. (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - Oh, Sung Dahm (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - Parker, John (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - Pisk, Krunoslav (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - Riaznov, M. (Box 17, Folder 16)
    - Ron, Akiva (Box 17, Folder 17)
    - Roy, Suprakash, Ch. (Box 17, Folder 18)
    - Salzmann, David (Box 17, Folder 19)
    - Sen Gupta, Swanpan K. (Box 17, Folder 20)
    - Serbescu, Liana (Box 17, Folder 21)
    - Shaffer, Charles D. (Box 17, Folder 22)
    - Sood, B.S. (Dr.) (Box 17, Folder 23)
    - Stein, Josef (Box 17, Folder 24)
    - Sud, Krishan K. (Box 17, Folder 25)
    - Thu, Le Anh (Box 17, Folder 26)
    - Tong, Xiao-Ming (Box 17, Folder 27)
    - Tseng, H.K. (Box 17, Folder 28)
    - Urnov, Alexander M. (Box 17, Folder 29)
    - Walker, David (Box 17, Folder 30)
    - Wang, Min-Sheng (Box 17, Folder 31)
    - Wood, Michael (Box 17, Folder 32)
    - Yang, Huang-Wang (Box 17, Folder 33)
    - Ye, Kuang (Box 17, Folder 34)
    - Yin, Ru-Ying (Box 17, Folder 35)
    - Yu, Simon (Box 17, Folder 36)
    - Zakowicz, Wtadystaw Btazej (Box 17, Folder 37)
    - Zhou, Bin (Box 17, Folder 38)